<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: comp-sci | holsee]]></title>
  <link href="http://holsee.github.io/blog/categories/comp-sci/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://holsee.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-04-28T17:05:35+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://holsee.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[holsee]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Don't circum to dumb]]></title>
    <link href="http://holsee.github.io/dont-circum-to-dumb/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-17T08:21:05+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://holsee.github.io/dont-circum-to-dumb</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I think brushing up on Computer Science fundamentals from time to time is a valuable endeavour, which every developer should do.</p>

<p>Even if it is as little as taking one of the many <a href="/mit-introduction-to-algorithms/">undergrad level modules online</a>.  Many of which are not to be sniffed at.</p>

<p>Surround your pullquote like this {" text to be quoted "}</p>

<p>My Sister is a doctor, and soon she will be revalidated: &ldquo;<em>Revalidation is the process by which doctors holding registration with a licence to practise will have to demonstrate to the GMC that they are up-to-date and fit to practise and complying with the relevant professional standards.</em>&rdquo;</p>

<p>I can&rsquo;t speak for what her day to day is like, but as a practicing doctor I doubt you exercise your entire base of knowledge on a regular enough basis to avoid refreshing yourself with the fundamentals from time to time.</p>

<p>Now imagine beyond doing our daily duties, developers were required to go through such a &ldquo;revalidation&rdquo; process in order to be allowed to hold the title of software engineer (or whatever).</p>

<p>An interesting thought&hellip; baring in mind we all probably know at least one <a href="http://techcrunch.com/2015/03/08/on-secretly-terrible-engineers/">Secretly Terrible Engineer</a>.</p>

<p>Ours is a industry fueled by both passion and science, and the passion is what has pushed us forward.  The same can be said for medicine.</p>

<p>Bad engineers probably were not always that way, maybe they were both sharp and passionate when they started, but the lack of inspiration in their 9 to 5 has caused them to become blunt and disenchanted over time.</p>

<p>It is often said software development is so broad and someone cannot possibly know everything, true, but I don&rsquo;t think medicine is a small field and there is no excuse for a Doctor to not be continually up-to-date with the fundamentals of their field as well as their respective specialization.</p>

<p>I for one don&rsquo;t like the idea of being made to &ldquo;Revalidate&rdquo;, but I do think we owe it to ourselves to try and stay fresh and up-to-date with the foundations of our industry.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[MIT: Introduction to Algorithms]]></title>
    <link href="http://holsee.github.io/mit-introduction-to-algorithms/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-17T08:09:53+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://holsee.github.io/mit-introduction-to-algorithms</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I recently got into a conversation about the computer science classic <em>sorting</em>, in particular we chatted about applications of Radix Sort.</p>

<p>Surround your pullquote like this {" text to be quoted "}</p>

<p>The spark rekindled my desire for refreshing my knowledge of the basics so I may build on this to explore the latest and greatest research in this area.</p>

<p>I personally like the MIT course <a href="http://ocw.mit.edu/courses/electrical-engineering-and-computer-science/6-006-introduction-to-algorithms-fall-2011/lecture-videos/">Introduction to Algorithms</a> as it covers so many of the fundamentals very well.</p>

<p>Watching &ldquo;Counting Sort, Radix Sort, Lower Bounds for Sorting&rdquo; at the minute:</p>

<p><div class='embed-video-container'><iframe src='http://www.youtube.com/embed/Nz1KZXbghj8' frameborder='0' allowfullscreen></iframe></div></p>

<p>A good start for now.</p>

<p>Also worth checking out: <a href="http://cs.stackexchange.com/questions/12223/practical-applications-of-radix-sort">&ldquo;Practical Applications of Radix Sort&rdquo;</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
