<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: otp | holsee]]></title>
  <link href="http://holsee.github.io/blog/categories/otp/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://holsee.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-04-02T11:05:27+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://holsee.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[holsee]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Thinking Like an Erlanger]]></title>
    <link href="http://holsee.github.io/thinking-like-an-erlanger/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-08T20:51:47+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://holsee.github.io/thinking-like-an-erlanger</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I found this video last night by <a href="LeHoff">Torben Hoffman</a>, I recommend folks interested in Erlang or Elixir give it a watch and take it to heart.  Torben does a good job of displaying how an &ldquo;Erlanger&rdquo; should think, in comparison to other programmers.</p>

<p><div class="embed-video-container"><iframe src="http://player.vimeo.com/video/118258580 "></iframe></div></p>

<p>Torben recommends 2 books which have been added to my reading list:</p>

<p><a href="http://www.usingcsp.com/cspbook.pdf">Communicating Sequential Processes</a> by C.A.R. Hoare. (Free digital Version)</p>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/Principles-Protocol-Design-Robin-Sharp/dp/3540775404">Principles of Protocol Design</a> by Robin Sharp.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Elixir, BEAM and OTP]]></title>
    <link href="http://holsee.github.io/elixir-beam-otp/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-29T14:25:42+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://holsee.github.io/elixir-beam-otp</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>As I plan to write and speak about Elixir on my blog and hopefully at some meet-ups soon, I though I would write a short post with handy descriptions of some of the key aspects that I can reference in one place&hellip;</em></p>

<h3>What is Elixir?</h3>

<p>Think Dave Thomas describes it best&hellip;</p>

<p>&ldquo;The Elixir Programming Language wraps functional programming with immutable state and an actor-based approach to concurrency in a tidy modern syntax.  And it runs on the industrial-strength, high-performance, distributed Erlang VM.&rdquo;</p>

<p>It has very powerful meta-programming capabilities through compile time expansion of macros and the dynamic power of the language.  A good example of the developer productivity that can be gained is their use in the <a href="http://www.phoenixframework.org/v0.7.2/docs/routing">routing system in the phoenix web framework</a>. When learning about Elixir macros I found the &lsquo;<a href="http://www.theerlangelist.com/2014/06/understanding-elixir-macros-part-1.html">Understanding Elixir Macros Series</a>&rsquo; by <a href="https://twitter.com/sasajuric">Saša Jurić</a> to be very useful.</p>

<h3>What is the Erlang VM &amp; BEAM?</h3>

<p>The &ldquo;Erlang VM&rdquo; is the name of the virtual machine where all Erlang code is executed. Every compiled Erlang file has the suffix .beam.</p>

<p>There is also an implementation of Erlang which runs on the JVM, called <a href="https://github.com/krestenkrab/erjang/wiki">Erjang</a>, but I guess the less said about that the better as the Erlang VM is really the awesome part if you ask me.</p>

<p>When you compile Elixir code it is converted to .beam format, which allows it to be executed on the Erlang VM.</p>

<h3>What is OTP?</h3>

<p>OTP is set of Erlang libraries and design principles providing middle-ware to develop these systems. It includes its own distributed database, applications to interface towards other languages, debugging and release handling tools.</p>

<p>The OTP libraries (and the associated best practices to an extent) are mature, battle hardened and hide much of the boilerplate code required to perform common patterns such as creating a server to store state, recover from failures through supervision trees and so much more.</p>

<p>I look forward to writing about this with examples in future as I learn more about OTP myself.</p>

<p><em>Where is OTP used?</em></p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/mojombo/egitd">egitsd</a> &ndash; egitd is an Erlang git-daemon implementation that provides a more flexible,
scalable, and loggable way to serve public git repositories.  It is used by github.com.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.rabbitmq.com">RabbitMQ</a> &ndash; An open source message broker (sometimes called message-oriented middleware) that implements the Advanced Message Queuing Protocol (AMQP).</p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/erlang/otp/wiki/Projects-using-erlang-otp">More Projects using OTP&hellip;</a></p>

<h3>Sources:</h3>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.erlang.org/doc/">Erlang Website</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/erlang/otp/wiki">Erlang OTP Source on Github</a></li>
<li><a href="http://elixir-lang.org">Elixir Website</a></li>
<li><a href="https://pragprog.com/book/elixir/programming-elixir">Programming Elixir Book</a> by <a href="https://twitter.com/pragdave">Dave Thomas</a></li>
<li><a href="http://elixirsips.com">Elixir Sips Screencasts</a> by <a href="https://plus.google.com/+JoshAdams">Josh Adams</a></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
